# 今天我伯爷摆摊留了一块猪肝 留回来专门炒
Today, my uncle brought home a piece of pork liver that he didn't sell at the market, for stir-frying.
# 先洗一下
First, wash it
# 洗一下一会儿那个纵纵就要散了
The wrinkles go away as soon as you wash it.
# 今天我们做一下嫩猪肝
Today, we make Nen Zhu Gan (tender stir-fried pork liver).
# 好 我们来开始切这个猪肝
Okay. Let's cut this pork liver.
# 我们炒嫩猪肝的话就要切薄一点
If we want it tender we need to slice it thinly
# 炒老猪肝的话就切厚一点
If we are gonna cook it for longer, the cut should be thicker
# 因为老猪肝切厚点的话它能够经得起炒
Thicker cut can withstand longer cooking times
# 我们切的这个猪肝大概的话是2毫米 不到2毫米
My slices are about 2mm thick. Less than 2mm.
# 我们切这个猪肝切着切着的话给它翻过来
Halfway through you can turn it over.
# 翻过来切另外一面
Turn it over and cut from the other side
# 你看嘛 这一面的话肉就暴露出来了就更好切
You see, the meat is exposed on this side and is easier to cut.
# 是啊
Yes
# 好 我们这个猪肝切好了放到盆里面洗一下
Well, our pork liver is sliced and let's wash it for a bit.
# 炒这个嫩猪肝你必须要切得薄必须要清理一哈清洗干净
For tender pork liver, you have to cut it thinly and clean it thoroughly.
# 嗯
Um
# 这个血水要把它弄来洗干净
We need to wash off the blood.
# 好 我们这个洗一下然后把它抓起来沥干水分
OK, let's clean and drain it
# 多洗几遍
Wash a few times
# 再洗一道
Wash it again
# 这哈就是第三遍了 这哈水就不浑了
This is the third time. The water is less bloody now.
# 好 我们这个猪肝已经洗了四五遍了
OK, our pork liver has been washed four or five times.
# 现在把它水挤干
Now squeeze out the water.
# 我们腌制前猪肝的水挤不干的话这个味道进不去
If we don't squeeze out most of the water, the marinade will not penetrate.
# 一下锅了这个味道就跟水一样就流出来了
And when you cook it, the flavor will escape like how water flows out
# 如果猪肝里面水分过多
If there is too much water in the liver
# 在没挤干的情况下你们放那个淀粉啊放蛋清给它码味
If you don't squeeze out the water before velveting (adding egg white and starch for marination),
# 一下锅炒的话会脱浆
the marinade will fall off from the meat
# 挤干水分这个是我们的一个规矩
Squeezing out excess water is one of our rules
# 如果我们炒菜不守规矩的话可能这个菜做出来跟你想象中有很大的距离
If we don’t follow the rules, the result might be not quite what you expected.
# 现在我们开始腌猪肝
Now we're going to marinate the pork liver
# 腌猪肝的话盐少放一点
Put less salt in the pork liver
# 因为猪肝有点敏感 盐放多了会有点咸
Because pork liver is a little sensitive to salt. A little goes a long way.
# 我们第一步首先要把盐放下去朝一个方向搅
Our first step is to add the salt and stir in one direction.
# 只有出了浆的猪肝它才会把其他的东西调料吸在上面
It allows the pork liver to absorb the flavors better.
# 要不然的话这个猪肝一下锅水分没有打干它容易脱浆
Otherwise, when we start cooking the pork liver, the marinade will easily separate.
# 现在我们这个猪肝已经把水分收进去了
Now our pork liver has absorbed the water.
# 收进去了之后开始来放一点胡椒粉
After the liver has absorbed the water, put in some pepper powder.
# 开始放味道了
Start seasoning.
# 放一点胡椒粉
Add some pepper powder.
# 少放点这个
Not so much!
# 好 少放点嘛
Ok, just a little.
# 然后放这个老抽
And then add some dark soy sauce.
# 放一点老抽调这个猪肝的颜色
Use dark soy sauce to adjust the color of this pork liver.
# 猪肝的话可以稍微颜色重一点没关系
It doesn't matter if the color of pork liver is a little dark.
# 好 咱们这个颜色就出来了
Ok this color comes out.
# 然后再放点这个蚝油 少放一点因为蚝油带咸味
Then add some oyster sauce. Just a little because it's salty.
# 主要是增加这个咸鲜味
We use it mainly for it savory, umami taste
# 好 这个我们搅拌好了之后再加一点淀粉
OK, let's mix this well and add some starch.
# 稍微可以多那么一点点 放一勺半
We can use a little more, one and a half spoons of starch.
# 淀粉就是把所有的水料调料把它吸在这个猪肝表面
The starch will help all the seasonings stick to pork liver.
# 好 我们最后一步
OK Last step.
# 这个油加一点进去 这一步非常的关键
Add a little oil. This step is very important.
# 大家这个猪肝腌好了之后最后加点油给它放一下
Add some oil after marination.
# 下锅的时候这个猪肝很容易就自动散开
The pork liver will spread out once put in the wok.
# 它不会说就黏成一团
It won't stick together or clump up.
# 然后这个也不容易脱浆
And the marinade will stick to the pork liver better.
# OK 现在我们腌好了
OK Now we are done marinating.
# 今天拿这个葱黄来炒 四伯爷
Today, let's stir fry with some yellow scallions. Uncle.
# 要得
Sure!
# 我们给它切马耳朵的斜刀
Let's cut it diagonally.
# 我们炒猪肝的蒜就随便拍一下就可以 不用剁太碎
For pork liver stir-frying, we just roughly crush some garlic. No need to mince it.
# 再放点泡椒
Add some pickled chili.
# 四川人炒猪肝不放泡椒要遭别人说的噶
As Sichuanese, stir-frying pork liver without pickled chili will be blamed
# 嗯 说你海椒都没得压不住腥味不好吃
Um, something like "Where's you chili? It's too smelly, not tasty at all!"
# 好 现在我们再做最后一步
Ok now we do the last step.
# 先给这个辅料调味
First, season the aromatics.
# 这个是我们四川的特殊手法 先调味
This is our special Sichuan technique, seasoning first.
# 我们放点胡椒粉
Add some pepper powder.
# 然后再放一点鸡精再放点酱油
And then some chicken bouillon powder and a little soy sauce.
# 好 再加点豆瓣酱就可以炒了
Add some Doubanjiang (broad bean paste) and then it's ready to fry.
# 四伯爷尝哈看
Uncle, taste it.
# 告哈看嘛
Taste it.
# 非常嫩
Very tender.
# 真的很嫩
Really tender.
# 这个吃这个猪肝要有吃法
It requires a special technique to eating the pork liver.
# 咋子说安 要蘸点这个汤汤
You need to dip it in this sauce
# 汤汤里头才是油 它才好吃
The oil in the sauce makes it flavorful
# 这个猪肝下锅到起锅十五秒钟都不到
The pork liver was only cooked for less than 15 seconds.
# 很嫩很嫩
Very tender, very tender.
# 咱们炒这个猪肝的时候油尽量可以稍微多一点点
We can use a bit more oil for stir-frying pork liver.
# 因为要把这个锅里面的整体温度提升起来
Because we need to keep the temperature high enough.
# 这个猪肝下去了之后炒几下 然后这个辅料下去翻几下就可以出来
So there's enough heat in the wok for the pork liver and vegetables to cook through in just a few seconds.
# 特别的嫩 很适合像我四伯这种
Very tender. Very suitable for my uncle.
# 我们这种牙口不好的吃起都吃得动
People like us who have weak teeth can chew it just fine.
# 很有好嫩 安逸
Very tender. Nice!
# 而且大家可以看一下你把猪肝的水分挤干了之后再腌
See? If you squeeze out the water from the pork liver before marinating it,
# 下锅炒它是不会脱浆的
the marinade mixture will not fall off
# 这就没有黏黏糊糊的 有些炒的猪肝糊起糊起的跟啥子样
This is not sticky. Some pork livers dishes I had in the past were a sticky mess.
# 跟烙的锅巴样
Or even too crusty.
# 这样子多舒服样 多清亮样
This looks clean and clear.
# 好了 本期视频就到这里
Ok This is it for this episode.
# 拜拜
Bye-bye